foreign
[Music]
suppose we have a right triangle with
sides of length A and B and a hypotenuse
of length C
we can take a second copy of this
triangle and place it here which forms a
square shape like this
we can also fill out the two triangles
to rectangles in this manner here
all three of these new shapes the yellow
Square the blue rectangle and the green
rectangle all have a side of length C
we can use the altitude of the original
triangles to then create the final
missing square up in the upper right
corner here
the full diagram that we have just
created is a square with a side length
of C plus h
therefore the area contained in this
square is the quantity C plus h squared
but now move the four triangles used to
create the two rectangles in this
fashion here
the resulting shape is now two squares
the upper right square has a side length
of H
and the new square that is diagonally
tilted has a side length of a plus B
therefore the area contained is the
quantity a plus b squared added to the
quantity H squared
this formula implies the Pythagorean
theorem let's see how by revisiting the
original triangle
this triangle had sides of length A and
B and a hypotenuse of length C and an
altitude of length h
we can expand the formula algebraically
like this and then we compute the area
of the triangle in two ways one-half
times the base times the height to
realize that a times b equals c times h
therefore in the equation the 2 times c
times H cancels with the 2 times a times
B and the H squares cancel from both
sides resulting in the equation c
squared equals a squared plus b squared
this ladder formula is known as the
Pythagorean theorem it says that the
square of a hypotenuse of a right
triangle is equal to the sum of the
squares of the leg lengths
foreign
[Music]